I think maybe the simple way you can do
is design three products or tiers for
the customers. Why? Because that's a
very common or easy way for us to pick
from. Some of one want to buy the most
expensive one. Some of just want to buy
the cheapest one and then some of one
don't know how to make decision and buy
the middle one. So that's usually the
simplest way for you to design your
product is because actually change how
decision are made. Let's say David if we
only offer one product. So your decision
is should I buy or not. But if a day
will show you three products now you are
thinking which one should I get? So you
bypass the yes or no and then more
likely to convert.
Hello, I'm your host David Bernard.
Today's conversation is shorter than
usual and will be featured in Revenue
Cat's state of subscription apps report.
Each episode in this series will explore
one crucial topic and share actionable
insights from top subscription app
operators. With me today, Sha Gong, a
product leader building monetization and
growth engines for consumer unicorns,
including Tinder and Grinder. On the
podcast, I talk with Shawn about how
Tinder's machine learning powered payw
walls drove millions in new revenue. The
art of selling features all a cart
without killing subscription revenue.
and why Tinder Select flopped despite
users saying they'd pay for it. Hey
Sean, thanks so much for joining me on
the podcast today.
>> Thank you so much, David, for having me.
It's such a pleasure. I always love your
newsletter, podcast, and all the
content. So, it's it's what an honor to
be here with you.
>> Oh, thanks so much, man. Well, I so I've
had several ex Tinder employees on the
podcast, but super excited to get you on
because I haven't gotten to talk to
somebody who's been in the trenches the
last few years and Tinder's done a lot
of cool stuff on the [snorts]
monetization front. So, I wanted to dive
into a project I know you worked a lot
on and that's AIdriven pricing. So, what
was the problem? What were you trying to
solve and and how did things go?
>> Yeah, I'm very excited. So let me start
with the core problem because that's
really you know shaped everything we
build at Tinder. Um so the user problem
is decision overload simplified to put
that way. So as you might know Tinder
has a lot of purchase options from
multiple subscription tiers and then
under each tier there is a multiple
plans like weekly monthly and then we
have a lot of allocart products. So it's
great right because we have so many
product for user choose from. However we
talk to users and we notice two things
at least. One is some user they bought
the platinum the highest subscription
tier we offer to everyone simply because
that's the most expensive one. So their
belief is that well I'm willing to pay
the most and then I'm gonna get the best
so I'm gonna buy platinum which is
great. However, we noticed some of the
users who bought platinum, they only
used the features under our second tier,
gold. So, they realized, oh, actually,
you um bought something you didn't even
fully use. You could have just bought
our gold subscription tier to save you
money. Or maybe another issue can be
like we can do a better job to educate
users. Hey, there is other feature from
Platinum. You should take advantage of
them. You haven't used them yet. Another
thing we noticed is some user they
didn't buy anything simply because they
were overwhelmed. It's like oh my god so
many options I don't know what to pick.
And then also reality we learn is maybe
David you have your own experience you
know when you look at particularly you
revenue c specialist in pay wall right
so one common mistake a lot of company
make is they describe all the features
or benefits the benefits are better than
feature yes however do you think user
going to read through them make a
decision no that's what we thought user
going to do okay let's compare tinder
plus tinder globe tinder platinum and
then compare the other car and then make
decision. No user make decision within a
second. So it's our job to help them to
make decision better. So that's from the
basically user problem is like decision
overload and then so it's overwhelming.
And then from the business problem is of
course that leads to relatively lower
conversion right because for some user
who wanted to buy but they were
overwhelmed they decide not to buy and
then that a lower conversion. So that's
a classic case of misalignment um
incentives. Um so we wanted to maximize
revenue but our UI experience made it
harder for user to make a confident
decision. Yeah. And I mean Tinder
famously I mean this is why I have you
on and so many people in industry have
talked about Tinder because it's led the
way in these hybrid monetization but
having three different levels of plan
and and then you you know you'll test it
out a fourth level of plan. We'll talk
about that toward the end hopefully if
we have time. But it does get super
confusing and then you have the super
the booths and the other inapp purchases
and things like that. So then what did
you do to actually to solve that and to
to make it more accessible to folks and
getting people to the right plan? So um
that was a challenging but luckily we
had a brilliant uh machine learning
team. So when I talked to the team
members and then they told me hey we can
try to build ML models and then use that
to predict users willing to pay and then
we can surface the best product they
might most likely to buy. So that's our
solution because based on the insight we
talk about is like people customers
don't need a lot of option they need the
right one right think about like Netflix
you know how many users like oh my god I
don't know what to watch there's so many
choices they end up spending like hours
scrolling and then not making watch
anything that's why Netflix have
something like top picks for you right
based on your previous behavior and your
ratings they predict what you're most
likely to to watch so solve that problem
so very similar So this is a huge moment
for us I think you know particularly
even for Tinder for the industry is we
shift from uh stale pricing to like
dynamic pricing so we don't show the
same pay wall same product to all the
users um so you know think about let's
say David you are willing to buy
platinum why we should we show you plus
right I mean that's a problem not just
from business perspective we won't be
able to maximize the revenue And then we
can use that to reinvest for to make
product better for you. Another problem
is you don't get to enjoy all the best
benefits we can offer right simply
because you chose the plus. Um so that's
what the solution come within. We use a
machine learning we train the model and
then we and eventually release a model
for that to predict and serve the best
skew for customers. How do you test
that? Like what was the what was the AB
test? It was just the standard kind of
deterministic
normal everybody gets this payw wall at
this part of the flow and then everybody
gets that pay wall at that part of the
flow. And did did you just do an AB test
to prove that the ML decision model was
was better than what you had before?
>> Yeah, spot on. Yes. Um but obviously to
reduce the risk um we couldn't just like
start it from all the pay walls, right?
because we have a lot of different payw
wall and then the same times that's very
expensive to uh and it takes a lot of
time and then effort to train the model
to test the model. So we start with
something small. So we test with couple
features um and then just you know start
with not all the scope. So we can see
hey based on this machine model to um
historically you know like a version a
control will be same you know like as we
used to show the payw wall and the
products to the new one this is dynamic
we will change based on the basically
when they show a user let's say for
David and then our payw wall will ask
the ML model hey which payroll should we
show and then the pay will decide okay
which product we should recommend to
David and then That's how we test this
treatment and then we'll be able to
measure the conversion and then the
total revenue and how how did it do?
That's great. Yeah. So I Yeah. So based
on our prediction, I think it's
definitely multi-million dollar annual
increase uh for Tinder. Also want to
clarify, you know, for that is like it's
not just like maximum revenue. It's like
a evil business plan. know it's like the
money we're going to use we can reinvest
to the product right so we can improve
our user experience and then build more
like benefits for customers that's why
uh when I talk to a lot of startup
founders I always advise them hey don't
wait to think about your monetization
strategy you know you don't feel bad to
charge your users they wanted to pay you
and they deserve it because you're going
to provide better experience for them
not mentioning to compete with your uh
competitors and you'll be able to move
faster and sooner.
>> What about counter metrics? Were there
anything you were watching to make sure
things didn't go south in retention or
user experience? You know, that people
weren't happy with with the plans that
they were uh presented.
>> Tinder has a really good process in
place and then we are required to also
measure our contract metrics. This is
great because you know this you cannot
only focus on on one area for example
for this case we cannot just only focus
on the first time conversion and then
only the revenue amount right so we have
to measure hey let's say David based on
our model maybe prior to that he would
buy a plus now he bought platinum so we
want to check hey is David going to come
back is David going to buy platinum
again it's going to cancel so we
definitely measure this long- term term
success metrics to make sure this model
really served correctly because that's
nothing we wanted to continue to work on
like a most product features right it's
not like launch and down that's it like
we have to optimize iterate so we wanted
to learn hey we actually have different
models we built a different ones we want
to compare so we want to see how they
perform between those model same time
how they perform compared to the the pay
wall without the models. So, we can make
sure we focus on long-term success. So,
the takeaway for this example is the
real unlock wasn't just better pricing,
it was a better decision design, right?
Helping users to choose a product they
truly fit them. Um so even for your
product you know any founders or
startups out there even you don't have a
ML team yet um I think maybe the simple
way you can do is um design three
products or tiers for the customers why
because that's a very common or easy way
for user to pick from right someone want
to buy the most expensive one some of
just want to buy the cheapest one and
then some of one don't know how to make
decision they buy the middle So that's
usually the simplest way for you to
design your product here is because
actually change how decision are made.
Let's say David if we only offer one
product so your decision is should I buy
or not but if a day will show you three
products now you are thinking which one
should I get so you bypass the yes or no
and it's more likely to convert.
>> Yeah that's fantastic advice. Um I I do
wish we all had ML teams. Maybe that's
something at Revenue Cat we should be
working on to help folks build those
kind of sophisticated things into their
own apps. But anyways, I did want to
move on to this idea of monetization
unbundling is that you know not
everybody wants the full subscription.
Not everybody is going to fit into the
gold the platinum. So yeah, how do you
think about unbundling that? We actually
you probably know we had some um
bundling products already car such as
like boost super likes I think a couple
thing you want to think about like
besides one issue you've already
highlight is not everyone want to have a
subscription right subscription is great
I mean don't get me wrong because you
get a package it's much easier than you
have to decide which features you wanted
to pick from and then to buy that way
it's it's painful right it's easy to buy
a whole package package and then repeat
it uh renew automatically. would have to
think about twice but there is some use
cases think about like boost I think
it's perfect allocar product why because
you don't it depends on when you want to
use it right when you don't receive
enough likes so you want to boost
yourself when let's say you swipe during
the peak hours so you wanted to use that
so that's makes sense super likes too
right because it's like well I don't
know how many super likes I'm going to
send it depends on who I see in the app
right and another use case we decide to
try is the travel mode also aka passport
mode. It's allowed any users to see
anyone globally. So it's so cool you
know like let's say you can go to like
Paris, go to Spain, whatever you want to
go based on your needs can be basically
you want to travel there or you want to
just meet people there and the thing
about that feature is like you may not
everyone wants it right maybe because
it's very special case for needs for
certain people in that case that feature
is a great candidate as like a unbundled
feature stand alone. So that's how we
think about what features make sense to
be unbundled and designed for our
customers. How does a passport mode
work? Is it a a one-time purchase for a
limited time? Is it an add-on
subscription or how does it work
exactly? Yeah. So, historically, this
feature is part of a subscription. So,
you have to get a subscription to use
it. And then, but like we talked about,
the challenge for that is for some
users, they only want to use it when
they plan to travel or to meet people
outside of their home city. And then
they might not want to buy a
subscription, right? because they just
don't want to have that commitment or
they don't want to they don't feel like
they need to use other features. So
that's a perfect candidate for them. So
we test out the features. So that helped
us able to capture nonsubscribers for
the users who just want to buy all the
car for this passport feature and then
they can use it for like one day, three
day a week based on the offers we
provided and then they can enjoy that
benefits to meet people anywhere in the
world. So, how have things been going
with the the passport feature and it
being unbundled from the subscription?
Have have you seen uptake? Yes. Um,
actually I I think it's it's so fun to
talk about this because it was not
launch and then success story. That's
it. Not that simple. We learned a few
things based on our test. First thing is
when we launched this um standalone
allocar passport feature and then the
conversion went crazy. It was great.
However, we noticed like, oh, that hurts
our plus subscription. [laughter]
Uh, because some user decided only buy
this feature, not to buy subscription.
But that can be a couple things. So, one
is, oh, maybe we price too low, it's too
affordable. And then so it's like no
brainer to user use it. The second thing
we did is like, oh, we should increase
the price for other card and to see how
that would change the conversion and
then subscription cannibalization. So we
definitely noticed that the sysun can
cannibization reduced as we expected and
then the conversion reduced a little bit
but total revenue actually went up. So
that was very positive and then we
continue to test because we wanted to
minimize the subscription kind of
positions. So and then we increase the
price again and then also have upsell on
the pay wall. Basically, we show, hey,
David, you can buy passport um
standalone alloc card, but also you can
buy plus subscription. And then we use a
very interesting like a kind of
psychology thing. Basically, for our
7day passport feature allocart, the
price is the same as 7-day plus
subscription. So, that case, David, you
think like, oh, duh. Then the 7-day plus
subscription is a better deal, right? I
can get it more than this feature. So
that also helped of course you know
means like reduce the cateization also
increase the conversion or revenue but
it's still not good enough. So we decide
hey let's use our perfect ML model
again. So we will show users
subscription first. If you don't want to
buy subscription we show you all our
car. So we give you a second chance. I
love hearing these kind of stories
because I just think Tinder's been
around so long and and so many of us in
the industry look up to it as a pioneer
in monetization in apps and I just think
so many apps are leaving money on the
table by not experimenting with these
kind of things and not trying all the
different you know three tiers and you
know and and like we said it can lead to
confusion. It's not the right thing for
every app, but there's there's just so
much opportunity to uh meet users where
they are and and charge them. And then
speaking of which, Tinder Select was a
really interesting experiment. So, I'd
love to hear from you how that went. You
know, it just sounds fantastic and we've
we've talked about on the podcast many
times before, you know, add a super
premium tier. You know, we talked about
it earlier like some people will just
buy the most expensive thing. So,
sounded like a really interesting idea.
How did how did things go with Tinder
Select?
>> Yeah, I think Tinder select a very
interesting case study in terms like the
product market alignment and the
behavior science. So let's start with
the hypothesis. you know basically the
opportunity Tinder was exploring you
know why Tinder created uh Tinder select
because Tinder has a massive global user
base and then we also have some whales
right you know basically the user who
are willing to spend a lot of money they
buy a lot of highest subscription and
then all the cards they spend a lot of
money with us um to maximize the outcome
so we definitely saw hey there is a
willingness to pay out there let's try
if we have a even higher end tier and
then provide even better service and
product would the user buy them not um
so that's basically the hypothesis we
had and then so that would be different
segment we're targeting obviously right
and then same time for the I think the
challenge are two things one is the
identity fit and the brand positioning
right you know because for any product
it's not every company can just offer a
high-end it's really rooted into like
what is your and is and then how
customer thinks like a good fit or not
right I think for Tinder because we
catering for the massive population and
then in that case it's um little bit
difficult to for some user feel like oh
you know it's good fit for me to use it
think about that David if we tell you
hey you're going to pay $499 a month for
subscription and then for on Tinder and
then when you come to Tinder you see
people you might be able to see even
just use a platinum subscription. Now,
you might think like, okay, I don't feel
that special here. Maybe you give me
some special treatment and benefits, but
I don't feel like the environment people
here that that special, right? That's
just difficult. That's very common. You
know, think about like a club too,
right? It's like exclusive one, very
expensive one versus just like a regular
one, but you have expensive table. So,
think about that scenario. I think
that's why make it challenging. It's
like a luxury offering, but people might
not feel the benefits meets their
expectations.
>> What's the future of Tinder Select? Is
it is it going away? Is it going to
evolve?
>> Yeah, I think this we're just not going
to expand much further and then just uh
gradually scale down for this one. It's
not like a fail is basically like we
learned what we initially wanted to and
then we realized it is not worth the
continue investment and the mitness for
us to have this feature. It's not the
best fit for us. We have better bets to
continue. Well, I think it's super cool
that you all tried and uh and a great
lesson as always that people don't
always do what they say in a user survey
or a user interview. So always a great
uh lesson to remember but you should try
and that that's the great thing and then
you did and you learned. Is there
anything you wanted to share with the
audience as as we do wrap up?
>> I think the most important thing I want
the audience to
realize or understand is don't treat
your users as they are logical human
beings. So what I mean by that is you
cannot think you cannot be like oh let
me design this product and the user
going to read everything on the screen
they gonna to make decision based
information I share with them and then
make a purchase decision whatever they
want you wanted them to do right no
reality they don't do that way um they
don't follow your user experience they
don't just read everything to make
decision so they are like us you know we
make emotional decisions
I think that's very important. So that's
why we have to really observe how they
behave and talk to them and to really
truly unlock the emotion behind that.
Otherwise you we're going to make wrong
decisions.
>> Where can people find you or are there
any jobs you wanted to shout out at
Tinder?
>> Oh yeah. I think Tinder definitely has a
still growing has a lot of fun
opportunities. So encourage people to
check out. It's one of the best places
I've ever been because it's really fun
culture, very progressive. and then
really care about people's life. When I
go to the cafeteria, every time I get
emotional because I see the the wall, we
show all the user who wrote letter to
us, show their wedding pictures. Oh, you
know, like our work, you know, made a
difference, you know, made people having
a new family together. How how lovely
that. And then same times also if you
wanted to grow your product and then
without hurting your retention and then
uh I can help you to unlock user
emotions and design defensible growth
loops and then you can find me on
LinkedIn and then mental cruise.
>> Awesome. Thank you so much for joining
me. This was a really fun conversation.
>> Yeah, thank you so much Davis. It's
always my great great pleasure talking
to you.
Thanks so much for listening. If you
have a minute, please leave a review in
your favorite podcast player. You can
also stop by chat.subclub.com
to join our private community.
[music]